<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bicycle Laboratorium - jobs</title><link href="https://mechmotum.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://mechmotum.github.io/feeds/jobs.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://mechmotum.github.io/</id><updated>2021-09-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><subtitle>E pur si muove</subtitle><entry><title>Postdoctoral Researcher Opening: Bicycle of the Future</title><link href="https://mechmotum.github.io/blog/bicycle-of-the-future-postdoc.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-09-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jason K. Moore</name></author><id>tag:mechmotum.github.io,2021-09-10:/blog/bicycle-of-the-future-postdoc.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://objects-us-east-1.dream.io/mechmotum/gazelle-steer-assist-bicycle.jpg" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Steer Assist Bicycle: an example bicycle technology developed at the TU
Delft Bicycle lab with Gazelle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="job-description"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Job description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TU Delft Bicycle Lab is seeking a postdoctoral researcher for a &lt;strong&gt;12
month&lt;/strong&gt; full time contract &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id2" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; with a starting date before the end of 2021.
The researcher will develop and …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://objects-us-east-1.dream.io/mechmotum/gazelle-steer-assist-bicycle.jpg" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Steer Assist Bicycle: an example bicycle technology developed at the TU
Delft Bicycle lab with Gazelle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="job-description"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Job description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TU Delft Bicycle Lab is seeking a postdoctoral researcher for a &lt;strong&gt;12
month&lt;/strong&gt; full time contract &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id2" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; with a starting date before the end of 2021.
The researcher will develop and execute an engineering research project for the
&amp;quot;Bicycle of the Future&amp;quot; grant which is supported by ClickNL
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.clicknl.nl"&gt;https://www.clicknl.nl&lt;/a&gt;) and Royal Dutch Gazelle
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.gazellebikes.com"&gt;https://www.gazellebikes.com&lt;/a&gt;). The aim of the TU Delft and Gazelle
collaboration is to arrive at design solutions that make the bicycle both safer
and more employable in society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will work on a project co-developed with the bicycle lab and Royal Dutch
Gazelle that fits into one or more of these three topics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bicycle-safety-solutions"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bicycle safety solutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making the bicycle safer from design changes, braking and traction control, and
tailoring the design and assistance to the skills of the rider. Solutions that
prolong and increase bicycling by the elderly are of particular interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="smart-mobility-solutions"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Smart mobility solutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloud connected electric bicycles open the opportunity to use data collected
from a variety of sensors (accelerometers, gyroscopes, GNSS receiver, torque
load cells, etc.) to improve transportation safety, efficiency,
personalization, and many other aspects. This topic should use this technology
to bring computer intelligence to bicycle transportation with a focus on the
vehicle's use of this information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="advanced-transport-solutions"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Advanced transport solutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric bicycles are being widely used to transport goods within urban
environments. This topic should develop and showcase new technology to the
design of electric cargo bicycles to improve the logistics and supply chain in
urban cargo delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Development of proof-of-concept prototype vehicles and vehicle technologies is
a desired outcome of the proposed research projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will work at TU Delft in the 3ME Faculty, mostly in the TU Delft Bicycle
Laboratory. You will work closely with and be mentored by Jason K. Moore and
Arend L. Schwab. You will also work with and collaborate with Gazelle
employees. Lastly, you will work with BSc, MSc, and PhD candidates of the lab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opportunities for growing your academic career will be available, such as
mentoring BSc/Students and PhD candidates, conference presentation, networking,
and grant writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="requirements"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have a PhD degree in engineering in mechanical or biomechanical or related
discipline by the start date of the position. If a related discipline please
justify in your cover letter. Excellent command of the English language is
required, as well as excellent communication skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="to-apply"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To Apply&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To apply, please submit (in PDF format) a 1 page cover letter explaining your
fit for the position and motivation, a C.V., an example peer reviewed
scientific publication where you are the primary author, and a 1 page project
proposal by 30 September 2021 via the application button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposal will be reviewed for novelty, feasibility, and alignment with the
stated project topics. The idea in the proposal will be used as a starting
point in developing your project with the TU Delft Bicycle Lab and Royal Dutch
Gazelle if hired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visit TU Delft's website to find more employment details and apply for the
position (vacancy number: TUD01463):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tudelft.nl/over-tu-delft/werken-bij-tu-delft/vacatures/details?jobId=4015&amp;amp;jobTitle=Postdoctoral%20Researcher%20Bicycle%20of%20the%20Future"&gt;https://www.tudelft.nl/over-tu-delft/werken-bij-tu-delft/vacatures/details?jobId=4015&amp;amp;jobTitle=Postdoctoral%20Researcher%20Bicycle%20of%20the%20Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applications Due September 30, 2021&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="additional-information"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about this vacancy, please contact Jason K. Moore,
Assistant Professor, email: &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:j.k.moore&amp;#64;tudelft.nl"&gt;j.k.moore&amp;#64;tudelft.nl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For information about the application procedure, please contact Ms. Anita van
Vianen, email: &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:application-3me&amp;#64;tudelft.nl"&gt;application-3me&amp;#64;tudelft.nl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id2" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;We originally advertised a 10 month appointment and the official
application page also reflects that, but we have obtained approval for the
extra 2 months. The position will be 12 months.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="jobs"></category><category term="bicycle"></category><category term="postdoc"></category><category term="engineering"></category></entry></feed>