<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bicycle Laboratorium - jobs</title><link href="https://mechmotum.github.io/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://mechmotum.github.io/feeds/jobs.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://mechmotum.github.io/</id><updated>2023-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><subtitle>E pur si muove</subtitle><entry><title>Postdoc Opening: Modeling bicycle behavior from visual stimulus to neuromuscular control ability</title><link href="https://mechmotum.github.io/blog/postdoc-bicycle-lidar-ad.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2023-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Jason K. Moore</name></author><id>tag:mechmotum.github.io,2023-12-14:/blog/postdoc-bicycle-lidar-ad.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="description"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TU Delft is seeking a postdoctoral researcher for a 1 year equivalent contract
(full or part time). The researcher will develop and execute an engineering
research project with the title &amp;quot;Modeling bicycle behavior from visual stimulus
to neuromuscular control ability&amp;quot;. This project is funded by a TU Delft
internal …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="description"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TU Delft is seeking a postdoctoral researcher for a 1 year equivalent contract
(full or part time). The researcher will develop and execute an engineering
research project with the title &amp;quot;Modeling bicycle behavior from visual stimulus
to neuromuscular control ability&amp;quot;. This project is funded by a TU Delft
internal Cohesion grant and is a collaboration between the Intelligent Vehicles
section and the Bicycle Laboratorium, both part of the Mechanical Engineering
faculty. The purpose of the project is to use Computer Vision and bicycle
dynamics models to accurately model cyclist behavior to improve bicycle and
road designs, as well as safety in sustainable transportation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accurate motion data on cyclists is scarce. Existing data has been largely
collected via counting at specific locations or GPS. However, the accuracy of
GPS is limited and there is no data that can track bicyclists with centimeter
accuracy in urban environments. We recently developed a bicycle equipped with
the latest automotive-grade sensors. By using visual odometry from IMUs, lidar
and cameras, we are able to drastically improve the localization performance
over GPS. We are further developing a perception system to detect other traffic
participants from the bicycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next stage you will equip cyclists with eye tracking devices to capture
their gaze direction during rides in crowded urban environments (e.g. the Delft
campus). The collected data will serve as input to a motion planner and mapped
to neuromuscular balance ability, i.e. reaction time and sensing quality,
needed to safely control the bicycle. By modeling how gaze influences decision
making and how vision interacts with vestibular and proprioceptive sensing to
maintain balance in safety critical maneuvers, you will gain crucial insights
into how individuals perceive risks such as stop signs and crossing
pedestrians, and the corresponding actions they undertake, such as braking and
counter-steering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="requirements"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PhD in an engineering discipline by the start date of the position -
Experience with machine learning for computer vision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strong scientific programming skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strong written and oral communication skills in English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ability to act independently as well as to collaborate effectively with
members of a larger team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following aspects will help you stand out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A strong academic track record with publications in topics relevant to this
position&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge of automated driving from perception to planning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specific knowledge of deep learning and data efficient methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge of human-machine control and two-wheeler vehicle dynamics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge of Python and PyTorch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that this describes the background we imagine would best fit the
role. Even if you do not meet all of the requirements and feel that you are up
for the task, we absolutely want to see your application!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="additional-information"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional Information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this role you will be embedded with the Intelligent Vehicles section in the
Cognitive Robotics Department and also a member of the Bicycle Lab in the
Biomechanical Engineering Department. Assistant Professors Holger Caesar and
Jason K. Moore will be your supervisors. For more information about this
vacancy, please contact Holger Caesar (&lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:h.caesar&amp;#64;tudelft.nl"&gt;h.caesar&amp;#64;tudelft.nl&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For information about the selection procedure, please contact the HR Advisor at
&lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:application-3mE&amp;#64;tudelft.nl"&gt;application-3mE&amp;#64;tudelft.nl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-to-apply"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to Apply&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apply via the TU Delft website application portal linked below. We will not
process applications sent by email and/or post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visit TU Delft's website to find more employment details and apply for the
position (vacancy number: TUD04759):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tudelft.nl/over-tu-delft/werken-bij-tu-delft/vacatures/details/?nPostingId=5301&amp;amp;nPostingTargetId=15445&amp;amp;id=QEZFK026203F3VBQBLO6G68W9&amp;amp;LG=UK&amp;amp;languageSelect=UK&amp;amp;mask=external"&gt;https://www.tudelft.nl/over-tu-delft/werken-bij-tu-delft/vacatures/details/?nPostingId=5301&amp;amp;nPostingTargetId=15445&amp;amp;id=QEZFK026203F3VBQBLO6G68W9&amp;amp;LG=UK&amp;amp;languageSelect=UK&amp;amp;mask=external&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apply by &lt;strong&gt;January 31, 2024&lt;/strong&gt; and include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a letter of motivation explaining why you are the right candidate for this job,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a detailed CV,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a copy of your diploma's,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the names and contact addresses of two or three references,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;any other information that might be relevant to your application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the available position will be filled as soon as possible (i.e. once
a suitable candidate is found).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="jobs"/><category term="bicycle"/><category term="postdoc"/><category term="engineering"/></entry><entry><title>PhD Opening: Discovering the Mechanisms that Cause Bicycle Crashes Through The Merger of Video and Computational Modeling</title><link href="https://mechmotum.github.io/blog/bicycle-crashes-phd-ad.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2023-09-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jason K. Moore</name></author><id>tag:mechmotum.github.io,2023-09-06:/blog/bicycle-crashes-phd-ad.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="alert alert-warning topic"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Filled&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This job has been filled and is no longer open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenge&lt;/strong&gt;: Quality bicycle crash data is essentially non-existent so we
have to use low quality videos from chance encounters to create accurate
reconstructions of the physics of these crashes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change&lt;/strong&gt;: We want to study how these crashes occur through …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="alert alert-warning topic"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Filled&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This job has been filled and is no longer open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenge&lt;/strong&gt;: Quality bicycle crash data is essentially non-existent so we
have to use low quality videos from chance encounters to create accurate
reconstructions of the physics of these crashes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change&lt;/strong&gt;: We want to study how these crashes occur through the lens of
physical simulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impact&lt;/strong&gt;: Once we understand how crashes occur we want to use the knowledge
to make bicycling safer and reduce crashes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="description"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are seeking a PhD researcher for a 4-year contract to develop simulation and
data analysis tools that lead us to understanding the mechanisms at play in
bicycle and other two-wheeler crashes. You will work primarily with video data
and computational neuromuscular models to develop the next generation of
predictive algorithms that connect human control to bicycle crash dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your project is partially supported by the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/eoss/proposals/opensim-creator-empowering-biomedical-research-with-biomechanical-models/"&gt;OpenSim Creator: Empowering
Biomedical Research with Biomechanical Models&lt;/a&gt;
grant funded by the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/newsroom/czi-awards-16-million-for-foundational-open-source-software-tools-essential-to-biomedicine/"&gt;Chan-Zuckerberg Foundation’s “Essential Open Source
Software for Science&amp;quot; program&lt;/a&gt;.
The software developed during the research will be contributed to OpenSim as
open source software and the research results will be submitted to appropriate
scientific journals and conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will simultaneously work as a member of the Computational Biomechanics Lab
and the Bicycle Lab both part of the BioMechanical Engineering Department. You
will be supervised by Dr. Jason K. Moore and Dr. Ajay Seth. You will work BSc,
MSc, and PhD candidates in the involved research groups from the BioMechanical
Engineering Department and other departments in the university.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opportunities for growing your academic career will be available, such as
mentoring BSc/MSc Students, conference presentations, networking, and teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="requirements"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MSc in engineering or similar discipline by the start date of the position&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience with simulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience with a programming language (e.g., C++, Python, Java, Matlab,
etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience with collecting experimental data (vehicle, biomechanic, video, or
similar)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good written and oral communication skills in English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following aspects will help you stand out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thriving in multidisciplinary environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-motivation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Curiosity-driven working attitude&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge of biomechanical modeling, vision based motion capture, machine
learning, control systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that this describes the background we imagine would best fit the
role. Even if you do not meet all the requirements and feel that you are up for
the task, we absolutely want to see your application! The PhD process is a
learning experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing a PhD at TU Delft requires English proficiency at a certain level to
ensure that the candidate is able to communicate and interact well, participate
in English-taught Doctoral Education courses, and write scientific articles and
a final thesis. For more details please check the Graduate Schools Admission
Requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="additional-information"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional Information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TU Delft Bicycle and Computational Biomechanics Labs are committed to
advancing diversity, equity, and inclusion efforts across open source software
development with this position, aligning with CZI's goals. We especially
encourage applicants from underrepresented groups in open source software to
apply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TU Delft values a safe, inclusive and diverse work environment. To reinforce
that, we have committed ourselves to the joint Statement Social Safety of the
Association of Universities in the Netherlands and the National Action Plan for
Diversity and Inclusion. In addition to that, we have a Social Safety
Programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing a PhD at TU Delft requires English proficiency at a certain level to
ensure that the candidate is able to communicate and interact well, participate
in English-taught Doctoral Education courses, and write scientific articles and
a final thesis. For more details please check the Graduate Schools Admission
Requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-to-apply"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to Apply&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apply via the TU Delft website application portal linked below. We will not
process applications sent by email and/or post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visit TU Delft's website to find more employment details and apply for the
position (vacancy number: TUD04370):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tudelft.nl/over-tu-delft/werken-bij-tu-delft/vacatures/details?jobId=15846"&gt;https://www.tudelft.nl/over-tu-delft/werken-bij-tu-delft/vacatures/details?jobId=15846&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the online application you will need to supply these things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Motivation and CV.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abstract of your MSc thesis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contact information for up to 3 references.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List of grades.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pre-employment screening can be part of the selection procedure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applications Due January 19, 2024&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="additional-information-1"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about this vacancy, please contact Jason Moore
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:j.k.moore&amp;#64;tudelft.nl"&gt;j.k.moore&amp;#64;tudelft.nl&lt;/a&gt;) or Ajay Seth (&lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:a.seth&amp;#64;tudelft.nl"&gt;a.seth&amp;#64;tudelft.nl&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For information about the selection procedure, please contact the HR Advisor at
&lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:application-3mE&amp;#64;tudelft.nl"&gt;application-3mE&amp;#64;tudelft.nl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="jobs"/><category term="bicycle"/><category term="phd"/><category term="engineering"/><category term="open source"/></entry><entry><title>PhD Researcher Opening: Safe and Efficient Traffic of Connected Vulnerable Bicyclists and Automated Vehicles</title><link href="https://mechmotum.github.io/blog/connected-bikes-avs.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2022-03-16T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-03-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jason K. Moore</name></author><id>tag:mechmotum.github.io,2022-03-16:/blog/connected-bikes-avs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="alert alert-warning topic"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Filled&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This job has been filled and is no longer open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://mechmotum.s3.us-east-005.dream.io/connected-bikes-avs.png" style="width: 300px;" /&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="description"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are seeking a PhD researcher for a 4-year contract in a multidisciplinary
research project to improve the safety of bicyclists and automated vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transportation of the future will include a mixture of automated vehicles (AVs)
and vulnerable …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="alert alert-warning topic"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Filled&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This job has been filled and is no longer open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://mechmotum.s3.us-east-005.dream.io/connected-bikes-avs.png" style="width: 300px;" /&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="description"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are seeking a PhD researcher for a 4-year contract in a multidisciplinary
research project to improve the safety of bicyclists and automated vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transportation of the future will include a mixture of automated vehicles (AVs)
and vulnerable road users (VRUs), like bicyclists and pedestrians. Unregulated
mixing of automated vehicles into urban areas has the potential to cause a rise
in transportation related death and injury. This mixing also exacerbates safety
concerns for vulnerable road users. Current VRU detection and its associated
trajectory planning are based on information that is collected solely from AV
sensors which is not sufficient to accurately predict the near-future behavior
of vulnerable road users. We want to validate the hypothesis that digital
information sharing among all road users combined with physiologically and
dynamically realistic predictive models can guarantee overall safety. Our
project goal is to achieve safe and socially acceptable interactions among
automated vehicles and vulnerable bicyclists in dense urban environments by
leveraging information shared in a two-way vehicle↔bicycle (V2B/B2V)
communication system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will be supervised by Dr. Jason K. Moore, Dr. Azita Dabiri, Dr. Frederik
Schulte, and Dr. Ir. Riender Happee. You will work with BSc, MSc, and PhD
candidates in the involved research groups that span the BioMechanical
Engineering, Cognitive Robotics, Delft Center for Systems and Control, and
Maritime and Transport Technology departments. Specifically, the PhD candidate
will have the opportunity to collaborate with others for human in the loop
evaluation in terms of acceptance and perceived safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opportunities for growing your academic career will be available, such as
mentoring BSc/MSc Students, conference presentations, networking, and teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are looking for candidates that can start during the summer of 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="requirements"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MSc in engineering or similar discipline by the start date of the position&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience with simulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience with a programming language (e.g., Python, Java, Matlab, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good written and oral communication skills in English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following aspects will help you stand out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thriving in multidisciplinary environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-motivation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Curiosity-driven working attitude&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge of control theory, transportation systems, machine learning, or
vehicle dynamics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prior experience with SUMO (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.eclipse.org/sumo/"&gt;https://www.eclipse.org/sumo/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that this describes the background we imagine would best fit the
role. Even if you do not meet all the requirements and feel that you are up for
the task, we absolutely want to see your application!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing a PhD at TU Delft requires English proficiency at a certain level to
ensure that the candidate is able to communicate and interact well, participate
in English-taught Doctoral Education courses, and write scientific articles and
a final thesis. For more details please check the Graduate Schools Admission
Requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="to-apply"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To Apply&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Submit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Motivation and CV.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A 1-page original research proposal with your ideas for addressing the
problems described in the description.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abstract of your MSc thesis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contact information for up to 3 references&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List of grades&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to the TU Delft website application portal linked below. We will not process
applications sent by email and/or post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visit TU Delft's website to find more employment details and apply for the
position (vacancy number: TUD02119):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tudelft.nl/over-tu-delft/werken-bij-tu-delft/vacatures/details/?nPostingId=2394&amp;amp;nPostingTargetId=6126&amp;amp;id=QEZFK026203F3VBQBLO6G68W9&amp;amp;LG=UK&amp;amp;mask=external"&gt;https://www.tudelft.nl/over-tu-delft/werken-bij-tu-delft/vacatures/details/?nPostingId=2394&amp;amp;nPostingTargetId=6126&amp;amp;id=QEZFK026203F3VBQBLO6G68W9&amp;amp;LG=UK&amp;amp;mask=external&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applications Due April 14, 2022&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="additional-information"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about this vacancy, please contact Jason Moore, email:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:j.k.moore&amp;#64;tudelft.nl"&gt;j.k.moore&amp;#64;tudelft.nl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For information about the selection procedure, please contact Anita van Vianen,
HR Advisor, email: &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:application-3mE&amp;#64;tudelft.nl"&gt;application-3mE&amp;#64;tudelft.nl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="jobs"/><category term="bicycle"/><category term="phd"/><category term="engineering"/></entry><entry><title>Postdoctoral Researcher Opening: Advancing Biomechanical Modeling By Improving SymPy Code Generation (x/f/m)</title><link href="https://mechmotum.github.io/blog/sympy-czi-postdoc.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2022-02-02T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-02-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Jason K. Moore</name></author><id>tag:mechmotum.github.io,2022-02-02:/blog/sympy-czi-postdoc.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="alert alert-warning topic"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Filled&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This job has been filled and is no longer open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;table border="1" class="borderless docutils align-center" style="width: 50%"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width="50%" /&gt;
&lt;col width="50%" /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;img alt="czi-logo" src="https://mechmotum.s3.us-east-005.dream.io/czi-logo.png" style="height: 100px;" /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img alt="sympy-logo" src="https://mechmotum.s3.us-east-005.dream.io/sympy-logo.png" style="height: 100px;" /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="description"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TU Delft Bicycle Lab is seeking a postdoctoral researcher for a 1 year
equivalent contract (full or part time). You will work on a sub-project of
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/eoss/proposals/sympy-improving-foundational-open-source-symbolic-mathematics-for-science/"&gt;SymPy's &amp;quot;Improving Foundational Open Source Symbolic Mathematics for Science&amp;quot;
grant&lt;/a&gt;
funded …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="alert alert-warning topic"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Filled&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This job has been filled and is no longer open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;table border="1" class="borderless docutils align-center" style="width: 50%"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width="50%" /&gt;
&lt;col width="50%" /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;img alt="czi-logo" src="https://mechmotum.s3.us-east-005.dream.io/czi-logo.png" style="height: 100px;" /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img alt="sympy-logo" src="https://mechmotum.s3.us-east-005.dream.io/sympy-logo.png" style="height: 100px;" /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="description"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TU Delft Bicycle Lab is seeking a postdoctoral researcher for a 1 year
equivalent contract (full or part time). You will work on a sub-project of
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/eoss/proposals/sympy-improving-foundational-open-source-symbolic-mathematics-for-science/"&gt;SymPy's &amp;quot;Improving Foundational Open Source Symbolic Mathematics for Science&amp;quot;
grant&lt;/a&gt;
funded by the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://chanzuckerberg.com/newsroom/czi-awards-16-million-for-foundational-open-source-software-tools-essential-to-biomedicine/"&gt;Chan-Zuckerberg Foundation’s “Essential Open Source Software for
Science&amp;quot; program&lt;/a&gt;.
The purpose of the overall grant is to improve the SymPy Python symbolic
mathematics library in the key areas of performance, code generation, and
documentation. The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.16590053.v1"&gt;full grant proposal&lt;/a&gt; is available publicly on
Figshare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We believe SymPy is the most widely used general purpose open source computer
algebra system (CAS). The software is over 16 years old and has over 800k
downloads per month on PyPi. It is a full featured CAS, with over 700k lines of
Python code. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7717/peerj-cs.103"&gt;The SymPy paper (Meurer, Aaron, et al. &amp;quot;SymPy: Symbolic computing
in Python.&amp;quot; PeerJ Computer Science 3 (2017): e103.)&lt;/a&gt; describes the software and some of
its uses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code generation plays a central role in SymPy’s roadmap for supporting
scientific codes. The code generation roadmap prioritizes usability, generating
high performance code, and supporting a wide array of languages. This
postdoctoral research project will focus on improving usability and performance
of code generation guided by a performance critical musculoskeletal model
application. This model will be adopted from a bicycle vehicle model and a
human upper body and arm model. This human-vehicle model includes stiff
dynamics, holonomic and nonholonomic constraints, thousands of algebraic
operations, and complex force definitions; all features that strain SymPy’s
ability to best competitors in advanced biomechanical simulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The postdoctoral research project has two primary outcomes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve SymPy’s numerical code generation capabilities for general use
cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a musculoskeletal driven bicycle model that demonstrates domain
specific improvements to the code generation capabilities of SymPy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The developed software will be contributed to SymPy as open source software
(BSD) and the modeling results will be submitted to appropriate scientific
journals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will simultaneously work as a member of the TU Delft Bicycle Lab and the
SymPy development team. You will work with BSc, MSc, and PhD candidates in the
lab as well as members of the SymPy community. You will work with and be
directly mentored by Jason K. Moore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This position offers flexible work hours, the possibility of remote work
(country dependent), and the possibility of full or part time work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opportunities for growing your academic career will be available, such as
mentoring BSc/MSc Students and PhD candidates, conference presentations,
networking, teaching, and grant writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="requirements"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A STEM Ph.D. by the start date of the position&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proficiency with the Python programming language&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good written and oral communication skills in English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following skills will help you stand out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open source software contribution best practices and experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience with SymPy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience with symbolic computation, numerical computing, and/or code generation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience with C/C++ or Fortran&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Computational multibody dynamics experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Musculoskeletal modeling experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that this describes the background we imagine would best fit the
role. Even if you do not meet all of the requirements and feel that you are up
for the task, we absolutely want to see your application!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="diversity-and-inclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Diversity and Inclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TU Delft Bicycle Lab and SymPy are committed to advancing diversity,
equity, and inclusion efforts across open source software development with this
position, aligning with CZI’s goals. We especially encourage applicants from
underrepresented groups in open source software to apply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TU Delft values a safe, inclusive and diverse work environment. To reinforce
that, we have committed ourselves to the joint &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.vsnu.nl/en_GB/news.html/nieuwsbericht/512"&gt;Statement Social Safety&lt;/a&gt; of the Association of
Universities in the Netherlands and the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.rijksoverheid.nl/actueel/nieuws/2020/09/01/nieuw-nationaal-actieplan-voor-diversiteit-en-inclusie"&gt;National Action Plan for Diversity and
Inclusion&lt;/a&gt;.
In addition to that, we have a Social Safety Programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="to-apply"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To Apply&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Submit (in PDF format) a 1 page cover letter explaining your motivation and fit
for the position, a C.V., one example peer reviewed scientific publication
where you are the primary author, and examples of your Python software
development proficiency (URLs to public code are encouraged).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visit TU Delft's website to find more employment details and apply for the
position (vacancy number: TUD01994):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tudelft.nl/over-tu-delft/werken-bij-tu-delft/vacatures/details/?nPostingId=2261&amp;amp;nPostingTargetId=5624&amp;amp;id=QEZFK026203F3VBQBLO6G68W9&amp;amp;LG=UK&amp;amp;mask=external"&gt;https://www.tudelft.nl/over-tu-delft/werken-bij-tu-delft/vacatures/details/?nPostingId=2261&amp;amp;nPostingTargetId=5624&amp;amp;id=QEZFK026203F3VBQBLO6G68W9&amp;amp;LG=UK&amp;amp;mask=external&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applications Due February 28, 2022&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="additional-information"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about this vacancy, please contact Jason Moore, email:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:j.k.moore&amp;#64;tudelft.nl"&gt;j.k.moore&amp;#64;tudelft.nl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For information about the selection procedure, please contact Anita van Vianen,
HR Advisor, email: &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:application-3mE&amp;#64;tudelft.nl"&gt;application-3mE&amp;#64;tudelft.nl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="jobs"/><category term="bicycle"/><category term="postdoc"/><category term="engineering"/><category term="software"/></entry><entry><title>Postdoctoral Researcher Opening: Bicycle of the Future</title><link href="https://mechmotum.github.io/blog/bicycle-of-the-future-postdoc-2.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-12-08T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-12-08T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Jason K. Moore</name></author><id>tag:mechmotum.github.io,2021-12-08:/blog/bicycle-of-the-future-postdoc-2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="alert alert-warning topic"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Filled&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This job has been filled and is no longer open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://mechmotum.s3.us-east-005.dream.io/gazelle-steer-assist-bicycle.jpg" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Steer Assist Bicycle: an example bicycle technology developed at the TU
Delft Bicycle lab with Gazelle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="job-description"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Job description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TU Delft Bicycle Lab is seeking a postdoctoral researcher for a &lt;strong&gt;12
month&lt;/strong&gt; full time contract. The researcher will develop …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="alert alert-warning topic"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Filled&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This job has been filled and is no longer open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://mechmotum.s3.us-east-005.dream.io/gazelle-steer-assist-bicycle.jpg" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Steer Assist Bicycle: an example bicycle technology developed at the TU
Delft Bicycle lab with Gazelle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="job-description"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Job description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TU Delft Bicycle Lab is seeking a postdoctoral researcher for a &lt;strong&gt;12
month&lt;/strong&gt; full time contract. The researcher will develop and execute an
engineering research project for the &amp;quot;Bicycle of the Future&amp;quot; grant which is
supported by ClickNL (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.clicknl.nl"&gt;https://www.clicknl.nl&lt;/a&gt;) and Royal Dutch Gazelle
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.gazellebikes.com"&gt;https://www.gazellebikes.com&lt;/a&gt;). The aim of the TU Delft and Gazelle
collaboration is to arrive at design solutions that make the bicycle both safer
and more employable in society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will work on a project co-developed with the bicycle lab and Royal Dutch
Gazelle that fits into one or more of these three topics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bicycle-safety-solutions"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bicycle safety solutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making the bicycle safer from design changes, braking and traction control, and
tailoring the design and assistance to the skills of the rider. Solutions that
prolong and increase bicycling by the elderly are of particular interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="smart-mobility-solutions"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Smart mobility solutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloud connected electric bicycles open the opportunity to use data collected
from a variety of sensors (accelerometers, gyroscopes, GNSS receiver, torque
load cells, etc.) to improve transportation safety, efficiency,
personalization, and many other aspects. This topic should use this technology
to bring computer intelligence to bicycle transportation with a focus on the
vehicle's use of this information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="advanced-transport-solutions"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Advanced transport solutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric bicycles are being widely used to transport goods within urban
environments. This topic should develop and showcase new technology to the
design of electric cargo bicycles to improve the logistics and supply chain in
urban cargo delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Development of proof-of-concept prototype vehicles and vehicle technologies is
a desired outcome of the proposed research projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will work at TU Delft in the 3ME Faculty, mostly in the TU Delft Bicycle
Laboratory. You will work closely with and be mentored by Jason K. Moore. You
will also work with and collaborate with Gazelle employees. Lastly, you will
work with BSc, MSc, and PhD candidates of the lab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opportunities for growing your academic career will be available, such as
mentoring BSc/Students and PhD candidates, conference presentation, networking,
and grant writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="requirements"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have a PhD degree in engineering or relevant discipline by the start date
of the position. If a relevant discipline, please justify in your cover letter.
Academic command of the English language is required, as well as strong
communication skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="to-apply"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To Apply&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To apply, please submit (in PDF format) a 1 page cover letter explaining your
fit for the position and motivation, a C.V., an example peer reviewed
scientific publication where you are the primary author, and a 1 page project
proposal by 7 January 2022 via the application button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposal will be reviewed for novelty, feasibility, and alignment with the
stated project topics. The idea in the proposal will be used as a starting
point in developing your project with the TU Delft Bicycle Lab and Royal Dutch
Gazelle if hired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visit TU Delft's website to find more employment details and apply for the
position (vacancy number: TUD01463):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tudelft.nl/over-tu-delft/werken-bij-tu-delft/vacatures/details?jobId=4904&amp;amp;jobTitle=Postdoctoral%20Researcher%20Bicycle%20of%20the%20Future"&gt;https://www.tudelft.nl/over-tu-delft/werken-bij-tu-delft/vacatures/details?jobId=4904&amp;amp;jobTitle=Postdoctoral%20Researcher%20Bicycle%20of%20the%20Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applications Due January 7, 2022&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="additional-information"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about this vacancy, please contact Jason K. Moore,
Assistant Professor, email: &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:j.k.moore&amp;#64;tudelft.nl"&gt;j.k.moore&amp;#64;tudelft.nl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For information about the application procedure, please contact Ms. Anita van
Vianen, email: &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:application-3me&amp;#64;tudelft.nl"&gt;application-3me&amp;#64;tudelft.nl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="jobs"/><category term="bicycle"/><category term="postdoc"/><category term="engineering"/></entry><entry><title>Postdoctoral Researcher Opening: Bicycle of the Future</title><link href="https://mechmotum.github.io/blog/bicycle-of-the-future-postdoc.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2021-09-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jason K. Moore</name></author><id>tag:mechmotum.github.io,2021-09-10:/blog/bicycle-of-the-future-postdoc.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="alert alert-warning topic"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Filled&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This job has been filled and is no longer open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="TU Delft &amp;amp; Gazelle Steer Assist Bicycle" src="https://mechmotum.s3.us-east-005.dream.io/gazelle-steer-assist-bicycle.jpg" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Steer Assist Bicycle: an example bicycle technology developed at the TU
Delft Bicycle lab with Gazelle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="job-description"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Job description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TU Delft Bicycle Lab is seeking a postdoctoral researcher for a &lt;strong&gt;12
month&lt;/strong&gt; full time contract &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#footnote-1" id="footnote-reference-1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; with a starting …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="alert alert-warning topic"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Filled&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This job has been filled and is no longer open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="TU Delft &amp;amp; Gazelle Steer Assist Bicycle" src="https://mechmotum.s3.us-east-005.dream.io/gazelle-steer-assist-bicycle.jpg" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Steer Assist Bicycle: an example bicycle technology developed at the TU
Delft Bicycle lab with Gazelle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="job-description"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Job description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TU Delft Bicycle Lab is seeking a postdoctoral researcher for a &lt;strong&gt;12
month&lt;/strong&gt; full time contract &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#footnote-1" id="footnote-reference-1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; with a starting date before the end of 2021.
The researcher will develop and execute an engineering research project for the
&amp;quot;Bicycle of the Future&amp;quot; grant which is supported by ClickNL
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.clicknl.nl"&gt;https://www.clicknl.nl&lt;/a&gt;) and Royal Dutch Gazelle
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.gazellebikes.com"&gt;https://www.gazellebikes.com&lt;/a&gt;). The aim of the TU Delft and Gazelle
collaboration is to arrive at design solutions that make the bicycle both safer
and more employable in society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will work on a project co-developed with the bicycle lab and Royal Dutch
Gazelle that fits into one or more of these three topics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bicycle-safety-solutions"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bicycle safety solutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making the bicycle safer from design changes, braking and traction control, and
tailoring the design and assistance to the skills of the rider. Solutions that
prolong and increase bicycling by the elderly are of particular interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="smart-mobility-solutions"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Smart mobility solutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloud connected electric bicycles open the opportunity to use data collected
from a variety of sensors (accelerometers, gyroscopes, GNSS receiver, torque
load cells, etc.) to improve transportation safety, efficiency,
personalization, and many other aspects. This topic should use this technology
to bring computer intelligence to bicycle transportation with a focus on the
vehicle's use of this information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="advanced-transport-solutions"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Advanced transport solutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric bicycles are being widely used to transport goods within urban
environments. This topic should develop and showcase new technology to the
design of electric cargo bicycles to improve the logistics and supply chain in
urban cargo delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Development of proof-of-concept prototype vehicles and vehicle technologies is
a desired outcome of the proposed research projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will work at TU Delft in the 3ME Faculty, mostly in the TU Delft Bicycle
Laboratory. You will work closely with and be mentored by Jason K. Moore and
Arend L. Schwab. You will also work with and collaborate with Gazelle
employees. Lastly, you will work with BSc, MSc, and PhD candidates of the lab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opportunities for growing your academic career will be available, such as
mentoring BSc/Students and PhD candidates, conference presentation, networking,
and grant writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="requirements"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have a PhD degree in engineering in mechanical or biomechanical or related
discipline by the start date of the position. If a related discipline please
justify in your cover letter. Excellent command of the English language is
required, as well as excellent communication skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="to-apply"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To Apply&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To apply, please submit (in PDF format) a 1 page cover letter explaining your
fit for the position and motivation, a C.V., an example peer reviewed
scientific publication where you are the primary author, and a 1 page project
proposal by 30 September 2021 via the application button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposal will be reviewed for novelty, feasibility, and alignment with the
stated project topics. The idea in the proposal will be used as a starting
point in developing your project with the TU Delft Bicycle Lab and Royal Dutch
Gazelle if hired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visit TU Delft's website to find more employment details and apply for the
position (vacancy number: TUD01463):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tudelft.nl/over-tu-delft/werken-bij-tu-delft/vacatures/details?jobId=4015&amp;amp;jobTitle=Postdoctoral%20Researcher%20Bicycle%20of%20the%20Future"&gt;https://www.tudelft.nl/over-tu-delft/werken-bij-tu-delft/vacatures/details?jobId=4015&amp;amp;jobTitle=Postdoctoral%20Researcher%20Bicycle%20of%20the%20Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applications Due September 30, 2021&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="additional-information"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about this vacancy, please contact Jason K. Moore,
Assistant Professor, email: &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:j.k.moore&amp;#64;tudelft.nl"&gt;j.k.moore&amp;#64;tudelft.nl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For information about the application procedure, please contact Ms. Anita van
Vianen, email: &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:application-3me&amp;#64;tudelft.nl"&gt;application-3me&amp;#64;tudelft.nl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="footnote-1" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#footnote-reference-1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;We originally advertised a 10 month appointment and the official
application page also reflects that, but we have obtained approval for the
extra 2 months. The position will be 12 months.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="jobs"/><category term="bicycle"/><category term="postdoc"/><category term="engineering"/></entry></feed>