<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Laboratorium of Marvelous Mechanical Motum - news</title><link href="https://mechmotum.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://mechmotum.github.io/feeds/news.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://mechmotum.github.io/</id><updated>2020-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><subtitle>E pur si muove</subtitle><entry><title>The Laboratorium is Moving to TU Delft</title><link href="https://mechmotum.github.io/blog/moving-to-tudelft.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Jason K. Moore</name></author><id>tag:mechmotum.github.io,2020-06-10:/blog/moving-to-tudelft.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;The lab is moving to TU Delft this summer.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;img alt="TU Delft Logo" class="align-center" src="https://objects-us-east-1.dream.io/mechmotum/tudelft-logo.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to announce that I have accepted a position as an Assistant
Professor in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tudelft.nl/en/3me/about/departments/biomechanical-engineering/"&gt;Biomechanical Engineering Department&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tudelft.nl/en/3me/"&gt;Mechanical,
Maritime, and Materials Engineering (3mE) Faculty&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tudelft.nl"&gt;Delft University of
Technology&lt;/a&gt; where I will join the Biomechatronics &amp;amp; Human-Machine Control
group. At TU Delft I will be leading a research laboratory and effort focusing
on bicycle engineering and related technologies. I will be teaching courses in
dynamics, multibody dynamics, and computational engineering to compliment this
effort and support the students in the department and faculty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this means that the Laboratorium for Marvelous Mechanical Motum will be
moving with me to the Netherlands. Over the next few years the lab will be
reimagined as it merges with the existing TU Delft &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bicycle.tudelft.nl/schwab/"&gt;Bicycle Dynamics Lab&lt;/a&gt;. The
primary initial topics of research will be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data driven vehicle and biomechanical modeling of the bicycle-rider system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data driven manual control characterization and identification in bicycle
balance and navigation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design and augmented/autonomous control for improvements in bicycling safety
and handling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Development of the next generation of bicycle designs for improvements to
transportation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application of vehicle dynamics to influence transportation infrastructure
design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance and safety improvements in the sport of cycling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are described more in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/moorepants/application-materials/blob/gh-pages/2019/tudelft/research-statement.pdf"&gt;research statement&lt;/a&gt; I developed for my
application and presented in the slides from the job talk below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe
src="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/e/2PACX-1vThi6LQvvs6Xw6AFr3HJTzGPSv2EOo5r1vSBlmqEsHK6WvDMqMKVi1DVMGm9U-rRspRPU76dCX33-DZ/embed?start=false&amp;loop=false&amp;delayms=3000"
frameborder="0" width="960" height="569" allowfullscreen="true"
mozallowfullscreen="true" webkitallowfullscreen="true"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;I start the new position on August 1st, 2020; so look for changes and new
announcements as I ramp up activity. I'll soon be looking for TU Delft MSc
students for various projects and will be reaching out to researchers,
companies, and organizations in Europe to develop new collaborations. Feel free
to contact me if you are interested in working with me and the new lab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am going to miss UC Davis. I've been here for the vast majority of the last
15 years and have learned so much from the faculty, students, and colleagues.
It is a bittersweet departure, but an exciting new adventure awaits!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="news"></category><category term="bicycle"></category><category term="biomechanics"></category><category term="control"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="engineering"></category><category term="sports"></category></entry></feed>